<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon Dr. Calamy's Discourse in the conformists cases against dissenters, concerning a scrupulous conscience wherein the nature of a doubting, tender conscience is considered, together with the duty of such as are proffessed of it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13617912</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13617912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 832:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon Dr. Calamy's Discourse in the conformists cases against dissenters, concerning a scrupulous conscience wherein the nature of a doubting, tender conscience is considered, together with the duty of such as are proffessed of it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by A. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1-2]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686. --  Discourse about a scrupulous conscience.</term>
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100797:1"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON Dr. <hi>CALAMY</hi>'s DISCOURSE IN THE <hi>Conformiſts Caſes</hi> AGAINST Diſſenters, CONCERNING A Scrupulous Conſcience. Wherein the Nature of a <hi>Doubting, Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is Conſidered: Together with the <hi>Duty</hi> of ſuch as are <hi>poſſeſſed of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. XIV. 23.</hi>
               </bibl> He that doubteth, is damned, if he eateth; becauſe he eateth not of faith.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed: And are to be Sold by <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> Inn, in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:100797:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100797:2"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON Dr. <hi>CALAMY</hi>'s DISCOURSE IN THE <hi>Conformiſts Cales</hi> AGAINST Diſſenters, CONCERNING A Scrupulous Conſcience.</head>
            <p>IT would contribute (not a little) to the healing of our <hi>Breaches,</hi> of we could come to a due Notion:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Of a Doubting Tender Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Of the Duty of ſuch as are poſſeſſed of it, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their own Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Concerning the Duty of Superiors, with relation to it in their Subjects or Inferior's Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100797:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of a lately-printed <hi>Sermon,</hi> called <hi>A Diſcourſe about a Scrupulous Conſcience,</hi> hath offered at two of theſe things:</p>
            <p>He hath undertaken to tell us what is a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience,</hi> p. 4, 5. and again, <hi>p.</hi> 35. he hath given us its <hi>Character</hi> (as he judgeth) <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. He hath <hi>directed us what to do to get quit of it,</hi> and how we ought to behave our ſelves under it, <hi>p.</hi> 18, 19, 20. and to the end of his Diſcourſe. He hath not meddled with the Duty of <hi>Superiors,</hi> with relation to it, in the <hi>Subjects</hi> or <hi>Inferiors Practice:</hi> That (it may be) is fitter for <hi>Chamber-Council,</hi> than to be publiſhed upon the <hi>Houſe-tops,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he hath fairly hinted it in his <hi>Epiſtle-Dedicatory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is a <hi>Scrupulous</hi> or <hi>Doubting</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience.</note> The <hi>Doubting Conſcience</hi> our Author calls every where a <hi>Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Conſcience,</hi> and tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <q rend="inline">It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about things in their own Nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and conſiſteth in ſtrictly tying up our ſelves to ſome things which God hath no where commanded; or in a conſciencious abſtaining from ſuch things as are not forbid, nor any ways unlawful.</q> 
               <hi>P.</hi> 6. <q rend="inline">It ſtarts, and boggles where there is no real Evil, or Miſchief. He knows not better how to illuſtrate it, than by thoſe inaccountable Antipathies that ſome Men have againſt ſome ſorts of Meats or living Creatures, which have no harm in them, yet are ſo offenſive and dreadful to ſuch Perſons, that they fly from them as they would from a Tyger or Bear: Juſt thus (he ſaith) ſome run out of the Church at the ſight of a Surplice, as if they had been ſcared by the Apparition of a Ghoſt.</q> 
               <hi>P.</hi> 35. he ſaith, <q rend="inline">When I ſpeak of a Scrupulous Conſcience, I ſuppoſe the Perſon tolerably well perſwaded of the Lawfulneſs of a thing that is to be done; but yet he doth not like nor approve of it, he hath ſome little Reaſons and Exceptions againſt it; it is not the beſt and fitteſt, all things conſidered. This is properly a Scruple, and is certainly the Caſe of all thoſe, who do ſometimes (to ſave themſelves from the Severity of the Laws) join in our Worſhip, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with us, which we preſume they would never do, did they judge it abſolutely ſinful and forbidden by God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is what the <hi>Author</hi> ſaith, to notifie to us the <hi>thing whereof he ſpeaks,</hi> and of which he afterwards affirms.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, it is worthy of our Enquiry from what <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution Office</hi> this Term of <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience</hi> (fronting the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100797:3"/>Book, and ſo often repeated in it,) is fetched. The Scripture ſpeaking often of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> (and that in the Author's Notion of it,) ſaith nothing of a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience;</hi> but hath brought all Complexions of <hi>Conſcience</hi> under that of a <hi>Perſwaded Mind,</hi> and a <hi>Doubting Mind,</hi> Rom. 14.5. <hi>Let every man be fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his own mind:</hi> v. 23. <hi>And he that doubteth, is damned, if he eat; becauſe he eateth not of faith: for whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi> There is not a Word of a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience</hi> in the whole Book of God.</p>
            <p>By what Authority we firſt create a thing, and then deſtroy it, or of what Significancy to the World any ſuch Imployment is, I cannot tell. But I take the Term to be only a <hi>Term</hi> of <hi>Defamation,</hi> for a <hi>Doubting Conſcience</hi> that is <hi>tender,</hi> and affraid to <hi>provoke a living God,</hi> knowing how <hi>fearful a thing it is to fall into his hands,</hi> Heb. 10.31. If the Queſtion were put, <hi>What a Chriſtian that doubteth of the Lawfulneſs of a thing in the Worſhip of God, may or ought to do;</hi> whether he may (according to our <hi>Author</hi>'s Poſition, <hi>p.</hi> 25.) <hi>take the Lawfulneſs of the thing upon Truſt from his legal Teachers,</hi> concluding himſelf no <hi>competent Judge</hi> of it himſelf: The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would have reſolved the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before he e'er could have got to the Parſonage-houſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>He that doubteth, is damned, if he eat not; becauſe he eateth not of faith.</hi> We muſt not therefore ſtate the <hi>Queſtion</hi> about a <hi>Doubting Mind,</hi> but about a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience,</hi> that is a thing hardly to be found in Nature.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> tells us it is converſant about things <hi>indifferent,</hi> things <hi>neither by God Commanded</hi> nor <hi>forbidden;</hi> ſuch things there are, even in the Worſhip of God, if we conſider them <hi>abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly</hi> from all <hi>Circumſtances.</hi> But thoſe very things may not be ſo, but either <hi>neceſſary or ſinful,</hi> according to their <hi>different Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions,</hi> and <hi>diverſified Circumſtances.</hi> Now what things are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> or cloathed with all their Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for this or that Perſon to do or avoid, is no eaſie thing for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to determine for himſelf, much leſs for another, who knoweth not his Circumſtances, to determine for him. It is very poſſible, a thing may be lawful for another to do, yea it may be <hi>neceſſary,</hi> which it may be <hi>neceſſary</hi> for me to avoid, and both upon the ſame Account, <hi>viz.</hi> avoiding Sin againſt God; for, in this Caſe, <hi>what is one Man's Meat may be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's Poiſon:</hi> So that what is truly <hi>indifferent,</hi> as to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100797:4"/>Practice, <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> we ſhall know at the Day of Judgment, but can no otherwiſe know it before, than from the Dictate of our own Conſciences; which, if they be <hi>fully perſwaded,</hi> Men may <hi>eat;</hi> but if they <hi>doubt,</hi> they are <hi>damned if they eat,</hi> (if St. <hi>Paul</hi> may be believed.) It was at that time of the Day a thing <hi>indifferent</hi> for Chriſtians to <hi>eat,</hi> or <hi>not to eat the Meats prohibited to the Jews;</hi> to keep, or not to keep one of thoſe <hi>Holy-days,</hi> which, before Chriſt's Coming, it was <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> for them to obſerve. All the <hi>Judaical Ceremonies were at that time indifferent;</hi> if they had not, <hi>Paul</hi> would neither have circumciſed <hi>Timothy, Acts</hi> 16.3. <hi>becauſe of the Jews in thoſe Quarters;</hi> nor <hi>purified</hi> himſelf and others at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Acts 21.26. and yet declare to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> ch. 5.2. <hi>that if they were circumciſed, Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing:</hi> Yet this great <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> (the moſt undoubted Superior) doth not determine, that thoſe that <hi>doubted</hi> might <hi>eat,</hi> nor determine them to <hi>eat,</hi> or <hi>keep the Days,</hi> tho' they doubted; but tells them plainly, <hi>He that doubteth, is damned, if he eateth,</hi> and only perſwadeth thoſe that did <hi>eat, not to deſpiſe thoſe that did not, becauſe God had received them,</hi> Rom. 14.3. and becauſe they, in not eating, were <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Servants;</hi> and, <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>the Kingdom of God lay not in theſe things;</hi> yet it ſo far lay in them, that if they doubted, they might not do them; and, <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>it was evil to eat with Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For our <hi>Author</hi>'s Illuſtration, and comparing theſe <hi>Doubts</hi> to <hi>natural Antipathies,</hi> &amp;c. in ſome Caſes it is proper enough; but admit the <hi>Antipathy inaccountable,</hi> yet where it is, it is very hard to deliver our ſelves from it; and I doubt not but our Author hath ſo much of a Man in him, as if he knew a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as I have known ſome) that could not endure a Room where a <hi>Cat</hi> or a <hi>piece of Cheeſe were,</hi> without continual <hi>Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sickneſs,</hi> and <hi>fainting,</hi> he would pity the Perſon, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>Cat</hi> or the <hi>Cheeſe</hi> to be taken out, and determine it mighty Cruelty for any to impoſe upon ſuch a Perſon, that he ſhould <hi>eat no Meat,</hi> if no <hi>Cheeſe</hi> might be upon the Table; nor <hi>ſleep in quiet</hi> in any Ruom, where a <hi>Cat</hi> ſhould not bear him Company. Such Impoſers every one would determine no great Friends to Mankind, nor to have any Compaſſion for the Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of Human Nature. <hi>Facile,</hi> ſaith he in <hi>Terence, quum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus aegrotis conſilium damus:</hi> But <hi>David</hi>'s Soul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.4.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100797:4"/>
               <hi>was exceedingly filled with the ſcornings of thoſe that were at eaſe, and with the Contempt of the Proud.</hi> Others might <hi>ſpeak as they do,</hi> if their Souls <hi>were in their Souls ſtead;</hi> they might alſo heap <hi>up Words againſt them, and ſhake their Heads at them: But they hope that they ſhould ſtrengthen them with their mouth, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of their lips ſhould aſſwage their grief,</hi> Job 26.4, 5. <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies</hi> are planted by the God of Nature; no mortal Hand can pluck them out. If theſe Doubts be as inaccountable things, yet certainly they ought no more to be called <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngovernable Humours</hi> and <hi>Prejudices;</hi> than the Child's forbearing to <hi>eat Cheeſe,</hi> notwithſtanding its Mother's Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Arguments, Intreaties, ought to be ſtiled <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>Diſobedience to its Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our <hi>Author</hi> is wonderfully confident to call <hi>Chriſtians Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents,</hi> as to the Lawfulneſs of ſome Ceremonies and Forms to be uſed in the Worſhip of God, <hi>inaccountable Antipathies;</hi> of which ſo great Men, as Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> Mr. <hi>Calderwood</hi> in his <hi>Altare Damaſcenum,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gilliſpy,</hi> (Men whoſe Learning cannot be queſtion'd but by ſuch as themſelves are the Enemies of Learning,) have given ſo large Accounts, to ſay nothing of the whole Churches of <hi>Scotland, New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. and Hundreds of particular Perſons, that uſe not to muffle their Readers with the blind Notions of <hi>Sympathies</hi> and <hi>Antipathies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 31. when he ſpeaks of <hi>Scrupulous Conſciences,</hi> he means <hi>ſuch as are tolerably perſwaded of the Lawfulneſs of the things, but yet do not like nor approve of it as the beſt,</hi> &amp;c. He ſhould have done well to have told us <hi>who theſe are;</hi> for we know none ſuch. <q rend="inline">Yes, he ſaith, this is certainly the Caſe of all thoſe who do ſometimes, to ſave themſelves from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of the Laws, join in Worſhip and Communion with them, which, he preſumes, they would never do, did they judge it abſolutely ſinful and forbidden by God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Some ſuch Perſons indeed we know, and are heartily ſorry that they meet with no better Encouragement than <hi>Apoſtate Proteſtants</hi> meet with from the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who, when they have firſt <hi>debauch'd them,</hi> then make it their Buſineſs to <hi>expoſe them,</hi> and <hi>ridicule their Religion.</hi> But in this Caſe there is no <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100797:5"/>and the <hi>Ridicule</hi> will return with Advantage upon the Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers uncharitable Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe who do ſo, do in Heart believe, that the <hi>Church of England</hi> is no <hi>Idolatrous Church;</hi> that God hath not ſaid unto it, <hi>You are not my People,</hi> and therefore they ought more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally to <hi>ſeperate</hi> from it, than to have Communion with it, in any thing which they judge ſinful; they therefore imitate our Saviour, who ſometimes went to the Temple, and to the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and to the Paſſover at <hi>Eaſter</hi> (tho' themſelves have not the Liberty he had to preach in the Synagogues and the Temple, which makes them not ſo conſtant there as he,) but had no Communion with them in the <hi>Traditional part of their Religion,</hi> as our Author excellently obſerveth, <hi>p.</hi> 1, 2. Nor did he tie himſelf to their Exerciſe of Religion, but often preach'd elſewhere, and that not to Four only, but Four or Five thouſand ſometimes: So as they do it not meerly to ſave themſelves from the Severity of Laws, but are thus far a Law unto themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But for ever to ſpoil our Adverſaries of this pitiful Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, and little Advantage of reproaching their Brethren, we will for once ſuppoſe ſome Nonconformiſts went to <hi>hear the Prayers, and received the Sacrament in Parochial Churches, to ſave their Eſtates, to ſerve a Turn, to keep an Office,</hi> (as others expreſs it) ſhall this conclude that they judge the things <hi>univerſally law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, under all Circumſtances?</hi> Things indeed, <hi>morally wicked,</hi> may never be done; things <hi>morally neceſſary</hi> may never be left undone: But certainly ſome <hi>mala prohibita,</hi> things which are only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, becauſe prohibited by a poſitive Law, and that do not reſpect <hi>Acts of Worſhip,</hi> or the <hi>Truth of it,</hi> but <hi>Rites</hi> relating to it, may under ſome Circumſtances be done, which under others ought to be avoided; and may under ſome Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be avoided, which under others may be lawfully done: Not that any thing <hi>prohibited by God, pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> may, <hi>hic &amp; nunc,</hi> be done, that were to ſet up one <hi>higher than the higheſt;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame thing, that under theſe, or theſe Circumſtances, is prohibited, under others is not. The Apoſtle determines to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that it was unlawful for them to <hi>eat Meat of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Idols, if they had other Meat to eat,</hi> or <hi>if their Conſcience doubted, or if their Brother was offended,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.28. which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100797:5"/>
               <hi>yet was lawful, if bought in the Shambles, v.</hi> 25. or ſet upon their Neighbours Table, <hi>v.</hi> 27. Our Saviour hath ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.5. <hi>That the Prieſts in the Temple <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane</hi> the Sabbath, and are blameleſs;</hi> and hath taught the <hi>Phyſician</hi> and the <hi>Chirurgion,</hi> that they may do the ſame in healing ſick or lame Perſons; and the <hi>Husbandman,</hi> that he may do the like, in giving Meat or Water to his Beaſts, or lifting them out of the Pit. The People were blameleſs that were not for Forty Years together circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Eighth Day, Joſ.</hi> 5.5. yet the Law was otherwiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.13, 14. Chriſt ſent the Scribes and Phariſees to learn the Meaning of that, <hi>I will have Mercy, and not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice;</hi> and certainly the firſt Mercy is to be ſhewed to our ſelves. I do not therefore at all doubt, but if there can be found a Man who hath Knowledge enough to diſcern the <hi>Lord's Body,</hi> and Piety enough to lay hold upon Chriſt, and apply Him and his Benefits to his Soul, who yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to receive the Sacrament at his Pariſh-Church: 1. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he did not like <hi>kneeling in the Act of Receiving;</hi> or becauſe <hi>he ſhould declare himſelf one Body with ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſons,</hi> or <hi>give Offence to other Conſcientious Perſons,</hi> &amp;c. and in that was blameleſs, and did what he ought, being at liberty: But under ſucha Circumſtance as this, he muſt do it, or ſtarve himſelf and Family, or lie in a Goal all his Life; he may do it. Many things are lawful, which no good Chriſtian ought to chooſe; and there are many things which under ſome Circumſtances he may chooſe, which under others were Wickedneſs for him to chooſe. Nor will <hi>Superiors Commands</hi> juſtifie the doing thoſe Acts which other Circumſtances will juſtifie. Superiors Commands will juſtifie none to work on his Trade on the Sabbath-Day; but the ſaving of a Man's Life, nay, the Life of a Beaſt, the quenching of a Fire in his own, or his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Houſe, will. But this is enough to ſtop the Mouth of this ignorant Clamour, and to let the World know that all are not <hi>Knaves</hi> whom ſome ſo call, and that ſome may be driven to a Sacrament, who ſaw no Reaſon to go without driving, and may, very probably, ſee as little
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100797:6"/>Reaſon to go, longer than till the Force (which was not good) doth abate, and be much leſs blameable than thoſe that drive them, or ſuch who in Obedience to that Force received the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but not the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> This is enough to have animadverted upon what the <hi>Author</hi> hath upon the Notion of a <hi>Doubting Conſcience,</hi> which he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly calls <hi>Scrupulous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He comes in the next place to <hi>defame</hi> it: This he doth (having told us it is the ſame with that ſome call a <hi>Tender Conſcience</hi>) by telling us,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q rend="inline">That it is a very ſickly, crazy Temper of Mind,</q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q rend="inline">That it is often a Sign of Hypocriſie,</q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q rend="inline">That nothing is more Troubleſome and Vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, </q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <q rend="inline">That theſe Scruples are endleſs,</q> 
               <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <q rend="inline">That it hath done unſpeakable Miſchief to the Church of Chriſt,</q> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> is the firſt Divine (at leaſt that I ever met with) who firſt deſcribed what he meant by a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience,</hi> to take to be a <hi>Tender Conſcience,</hi> and then told the World, <q rend="inline">It was a very ſickly, crazy Temper of Mind, a great Indiſpoſition, a State of Weakneſs and Infirmity, ariſing from Ignorance, and want of right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Religion; from undue Timerouſneſs, or Unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tledneſs of Mind; from Melancholy, or unreaſonable Prejudices and Miſtakes about the Nature of Things.</q> What is? what can be a Tenderneſs of Conſcience, but a <hi>Fear of Offending the Great and Living God?</hi> It is true, it is poſſible this may be too much, and often is, when ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged from <hi>Melancholy,</hi> which naturally influenceth the Mind with <hi>Fear.</hi> It is as true, that <hi>Fear</hi> may ſometimes ariſe from <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and that all Fear, reſpecting <hi>Actions</hi> to be done, doth ſo; (there will therefore be no ſuch Fear in Heaven, where we ſhall no longer <hi>know in part,</hi> but as we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100797:6"/>are known.) But <hi>Knowledge in part</hi> is our higheſt Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this Life, which giveth a juſt Ground of <hi>Fear;</hi> and indeed, ſetting aſide the <hi>Reverential Fear of God,</hi> (which is what will be found in Heaven) I do not know what that <hi>Fear of God</hi> is, by which all <hi>Religion</hi> is uſually expreſſed in Scripture, but <hi>a Fear of offending God;</hi> and tho' it ariſeth out of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> yet it is no <hi>ſickly, crazy Temper,</hi> but as perfect a State of Heart as any Soul can have, not cured of the <hi>Mortality</hi> of the Body which it informeth. According to <hi>Degrees of Knowledge,</hi> ſo are <hi>Degrees of Fear,</hi> leſs or greater. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.14. <hi>Happy is he who feareth alway: but he that hardeneth his heart, ſhall fall into miſchief.</hi> Religion is oft deſcribed by <hi>Fearing God,</hi> but never by <hi>Confidence,</hi> or <hi>Boldneſs,</hi> or <hi>Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart.</hi> Indeed, an Overfearfulneſs, or <hi>fearing where no Fear is,</hi> is a great Evil: But who ſhall judge of that? The Want of this <hi>Externus Judex</hi> ſpoils all, and where to find him we cannot tell; for he is not to be found in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, as to things to be done. If a Man's own Conſcience muſt be Judge, as to his Practice, an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verfearfulneſs is rather a Man's Misfortune than his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sin. I ſhould not have adventured to call it a <hi>crazy Temper,</hi> leſt ſome ſhould think that I ſhould think that much Fear of God can make Men mad.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is very true, that an over-much <hi>Serupuloſity</hi> may be <hi>ſometimes a Sign of Hypocriſie;</hi> but never is ſo, unleſs in the Caſe he mentions of the Phariſees, <hi>when Men ſtrain at Gnats, and ſwallow Camels:</hi> Let thoſe who do ſo bear their Blame, and endure the Imputation of Hypocrites. But want does this concern others? <hi>Making long Prayers</hi> is alſo by our Saviour made a Mark of <hi>Hypocriſie;</hi> but it is only ſo when it is done in <hi>Pretence</hi> to cover the <hi>devouring Widows Houſes.</hi> Our Author needed not to have told us, <q rend="inline"> That they who pretend to ſuch tender Conſciences above other Men, muſt know, that the World will watch them as to the Fairneſs and Juſtice of their Dealings, the Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Tempers, their Behaviour in their ſeveral
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100797:7"/>relations, their Modeſty, Humility, Charity, Peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the like;</q> becauſe the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> hath told us ſo, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. <hi>For I heard the defaming of many, fear on every ſide: Report, ſay they, and we will report: All my familiars watched for my halting: Peradventure he will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed, and we ſhall prevail againſt him, and take our revenge upon him.</hi> But beſides, all this is built upon this Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That every Man is an Hypocrite, who pretendeth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in one thing, and ſheweth it not in all things,</hi> becauſe <hi>Conſcience is uniform.</hi> Then he granteth, That every one that doth go to his <hi>Pariſh-Church,</hi> and there <hi>receiveth the Sacrament,</hi> according to all the <hi>Rites of the Church,</hi> yet is an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> if he be a <hi>Common Drunkard, Swearer, Lyar, Sabbath-breaker, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt in his Dealings, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable,</hi> an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkind, Husband</hi> or <hi>Wife,</hi> a <hi>Rebellious</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndutiful Child, Impudent, Proud, Turbulent, Quarrelſome,</hi> an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> &amp;c. For the ſame Reaſon that concludeth the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,</hi> ſo, for not going, yet being any of theſe ways guilty, will alſo conclude the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> ſo. If he be guilty, this will make Multitudes of Tranſgreſſors on Both ſides, and not leave any great Crouds on either ſides Maſters of any Conſcience: And after this, we need not propound the Queſtion, <hi>Are there few that ſhall be ſaved? Res ipſa loquitur.</hi> It is true, that a True Good Conſcience equally obligeth to every piece of the <hi>Divine Law,</hi> where the Mind is equally enlightned: But that every Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that is not an Hypocrite, will follow the Obligation to every part, with an equal Pace, I dare not ſay. It is as he apprehendeth the more or leſs hainous Nature of the Sin. It is commonly obſerved, that God is <hi>moſt Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in the Matters of his Worſhip;</hi> the Holy Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it, the Wrath of God hath, from time to time, been moſt ſeverely revealed againſt ſuch Sins; and that not in the Caſe of <hi>Idolatry</hi> alone, (for that was neither the Caſe of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abibu,</hi> nor yet of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> or <hi>Saul.</hi>) It is not therefore to be concluded, that that Man that is tender in theſe things, is an <hi>Hypocrite;</hi> tho' he may, as to ſome things, fail in his Dealings in Fairneſs, or Juſtice,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100797:7"/>(if ſome may be Judges eſpecially) or be guilty of what ſome Men call <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors.</hi> Even St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, who durſt deliver unto his <hi>Coirnthians</hi> no more than <hi>what he had received from the Lord,</hi> was yet by <hi>Tertullus, Acts</hi> 24.5. ſtiled a <hi>Peſtilent Fellow, and a mover of Sedition amongſt all the Jews throughout the World, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazarenes;</hi> which was as much as a <hi>Factions Perſon,</hi> and a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> and <hi>Diſobedient to Superiors.</hi> By the ſame Reaſon, that a Man may more fear <hi>Murther</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> than a little <hi>unconſcionable Gain,</hi> or <hi>Petty-Laceny,</hi> even a Conſcientious Man may fear <hi>Deviations</hi> from the <hi>Rule of Worſhip,</hi> more than ſome other Errors of his Life, either not known to him, or not of the higheſt <hi>Magnitude.</hi> But, I truſt, the World ſhall ſee, and in part doth ſee, the Generality of <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> as much affraid of a Lewd and Prophane Life, as they are of doing what is ſuperfluous, or (as they apprehend) <hi>forbidden in the Worſhip of God.</hi> If there be a <hi>Judas</hi> amongſt the Twelve, he will not determine all the reſt <hi>Traitors,</hi> I hope; for they generally let the World judge on which ſide are the moſt (Number for Number) Men of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> in giving to every one their due Right; or <hi>Charity, in giving Alms of ſuch Things as they have;</hi> or <hi>Modeſty,</hi> in their Speeches or Behaviours.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is very true, that there is nothing more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome than <hi>unreaſonable Scruples:</hi> But what is this to thoſe that have a <hi>moral Certainty</hi> of the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of things? which is as much as Men can have as to the moſt of things to be done or avoided: There are very few <hi>Diſſenters</hi> but do at leaſt pretend to this, as to thoſe things they boggle at, believing things may by Circumſtances be made <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,</hi> which, poſſibly, under other Circumſtances would not be ſo, as well as other things which are againſt the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> or the expreſs Letter of the <hi>Divine Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100797:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. For the <hi>Infiniteneſs of Scruples,</hi> it is but aſſerted; nor will it follow, that becauſe ſome particular Perſons may ſcruple or doubt any thing, therefore it is the beſt way to fear, or doubt of nothing.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nor doth it follow, that becauſe the <hi>needleſs ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling lawful things hath done Miſchief to the Church,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none may doubt the Lawfulneſs of the things which others ſay are <hi>lawful,</hi> and while they doubt, forbear the doing of them; eſpecially conſidering, that if the things be but <hi>lawful,</hi> they are not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be impoſed upon any. This our <hi>Author</hi> is aware of, <hi>p.</hi> 26. and tells us, <q rend="inline">He only conſidereth things as they ſtand, and will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Duty of Superiors, how far they may, or ought to condeſcend to the Weakneſs of others.</q> He tells us alſo further, <q rend="inline">That if this were a ſufficient Reaſon why the Conſtitution of any Church ſhould be altered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome things are ſcrupled in it, there would never be any ſettled Church while the World ſtands.</q>— There is nothing now doubted by any ſober Perſon, but what was doubted, and the Reaſons of thoſe Doubts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded before any ſuch <hi>Conſtitution</hi> was, (if he means that we were conſtituted by the laſt Act of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi>) If the Reaſons did not ſeem ſufficient to the <hi>Authors</hi> of that <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> we cannot help it; they then did, and yet do appear ſo unto many, and that not only of the preſent, but the former Ages, and that not in <hi>our own Church</hi> only, but are done in no other <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> (except the <hi>Lutheran Churches</hi>) from whom our Church alſo in other things enough differeth. Still we want a <hi>Judex externus de agendis,</hi> one that ſhall infallibly judge for others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Duty:</hi> For if a Man's Conſcience only can execute that Office, the <hi>Superior</hi> indeed (being Judge of his own Act) may inforce, impriſon, ruine Men and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, for not obeying what he granteth he is under no Neceſſity to command. The Inferior, that judgeth the thing <hi>ſinful,</hi> muſt lie in Priſon, ſatisfying himſelf with the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100797:8"/>Liberty of his Spirit, and take the ſpoiling of his Goods joyfully, believing that he hath in Heaven a better and far more enduring Subſtance, or ſuffer Exile, <hi>looking for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Country;</hi> and it muſt be determined at the laſt Day who is in the Right: And when all is ſaid that can be, this is all that the Word of God will allow any <hi>Inferior</hi> in the Caſe, ſave that it will oblige him to uſe the beſt Means he can further to inform himſelf; in order to which, our Author is ſo Charitable as to lend us his <hi>Candle:</hi> Let us ſee if, by all the Endeavours we can uſe, we can light ours by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Firſt Direction is excellent, <hi>viz. To beget and cheriſh in our Minds the Moſt High, and Worthy, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Thoughts of God Almighty:</hi> But his Enlargements on this Head we cannot ſo well agree. Had it not been <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> for any Perſon to have argued thus: <q rend="inline">Can the Man have becoming and excellent Thoughts of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, who imagineth that he regards whether the Ark be carried on a Cart, or upon Mens Shoulders; whether the Fire drops from Heaven, or be taken out of the Kitchen, by which Incenſe is burned to him?</q> If any ſay we are not under the ſame Diſpenſation, was there then in theſe things any thing either Typical or Carnal? Hath not God as ſufficiently revealed his Will for Goſpel, as for Legal Worſhip? He certainly hath the <hi>moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Thoughts of God,</hi> who thinks him the fitteſt to direct his own Homage, and not one whoſe Wiſdom ought to be controlled, or may be ſo much as tacitly impeached. The Phraſes of thinking to <hi>Flatter</hi> or <hi>Humour God,</hi> might have been ſpared by one adviſing others to <hi>High, Worthy, and Honourable Thoughts of God. Offer them now to a Prince, will they be accepted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas the Author adviſeth us to <hi>lay out our great Care about neceſſary and ſubſtantial Duties,</hi> he ſpeaketh well; the Apoſtle indeed doth tell us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. <hi>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is not meat and drink, but righteouſneſs, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100797:9"/>peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> in the ſame Senſe that the Prophet tells us, <hi>God will have mercy, and not ſacrifice:</hi> But if this be urged to perſwade us to do things, the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of which we doubt, whoſo urgeth it, is confuted by the laſt Words of the ſame Chapter; <hi>He that doubteth, is damned, if he eateth; becauſe he eateth not of faith: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi> It is indeed a Text well ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to let thoſe that <hi>eat</hi> know it is their Duty, not to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe,</hi> not to <hi>judge,</hi> much leſs to ruine and undoe thoſe that doubtingly dare not eat, and can meet with no Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to their Doubts, tho' they diligently <hi>ſeek and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We needed not therefore our <hi>Author</hi>'s Advice, to be <hi>willing to receive Satisfaction,</hi> if the Deſires of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> the <hi>Goodneſs of our Natures, our Love to our Wives and Children,</hi> would not obtain this of us: Yet ſurely the deſtroying of our Healths by naſty Priſons, the taking away our Eſtates, would, e're this time, have made us willing, if it had been poſſible for us, to have believed what we liſted, or the Dread of God had not awed us from doing, what we believe is not lawful for us to do. We have read the Books wrote on theſe Arguments, but it is our Unhappineſs that we cannot find the Queſtion truly ſtated. If we tell them a thouſand times, that we queſtion not the Lawfulneſs of ſome <hi>Circumſtances</hi> to be appointed in Worſhip, but of appointing <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Rites</hi> entailed to Acts of Worſhip; ſtill we find the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> ſtated about <hi>Circumſtances, Whether Superiors may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them?</hi> Let us often tell them, the Queſtion is not, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may do things which we ſcruple?</hi> but, Whether we may do things which we by <hi>Arguments,</hi> which we cannot anſwer, do judge <hi>unlawful?</hi> yet the next time the Queſtion is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhall be about <hi>Scruples?</hi> Tell them, the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is not about <hi>things indifferent,</hi> but <hi>things</hi> which (whatever O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion Superiors have of them) we judge <hi>ſinful;</hi> ſtill <hi>(will we, nill we,)</hi> it muſt be taken for granted, that the things are <hi>indifferent.</hi> If we tell them, the Queſtion is not about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100797:9"/>
               <hi>the Lawfulneſs of Forms of Prayer,</hi> nor yet of the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Uſe in <hi>Devotion,</hi> as well as for <hi>Inſtruction;</hi> but of the Lawfulneſs of the <hi>univerſal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of them</hi> by all Perſons, and thoſe Forms too not preſcribed by God, nor made by him that himſelf afterwards uſeth them, but ſuch as are made for our Uſe by other Men, and impoſed on us; the next time the Queſtion is ſtated, it ſhall be about the <hi>Lawfulneſs of Forms of Prayer,</hi> a thing we never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied. We would be very glad if our <hi>Reverend Author</hi> could direct us to any one Book, where the Queſtions we inſiſt upon are truly ſtated, and the Part oppoſite to us cloſely argued, and we not only preſſed with the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of meer <hi>Authority commanding,</hi> and the Practice of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> when 'tis certain Superiors are not to be obey'd in all things, and we cannot find any ſuch <hi>Antiquity;</hi> nor, if we could, can judge it a ſufficient Guide to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
            <p>We do not deſpiſe, nor neglect (ſome of us at leaſt) to go to our Miniſters, nay, to ſome <hi>Parochial Miniſters,</hi> (tho' we could never underſtand <hi>Pariſhes, Jure Divino;</hi> nor the <hi>Rectors,</hi> or <hi>Vicars,</hi> or <hi>Curates,</hi> of or in them, as ſuch, to be ſo; tho' we own a Miniſtry, and their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry (many of them we mean) to be ſuch,) but all that we can hear from them, is, <hi>The things commanded, are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; being commanded, you are bound to obey your Superiors: If not, we muſt preſent you,</hi> &amp;c. When we tell them, That if we could judge them <hi>indifferent,</hi> our Obedience would be Matter of Diſpute to none or few of us; but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo judge them. They indeed tell us, <hi>God hath no where forbidden them;</hi> but when we reply, Neither hath God in any Letter of Scripture forbidden us <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Salt,</hi> and <hi>Cream,</hi> and <hi>Spittle,</hi> or <hi>Oil,</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> yet, were theſe things commanded, we could not judge them law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe of no <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> no <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> we cannot hear any thing ſatisfactorily replied. We own our ſelves bound to <hi>obey Superiors in things lawful,</hi> but we cannot allow our <hi>Superiors,</hi> as to our <hi>Practice,</hi> to be <hi>Judges
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100797:10"/>of things always lawful in God's Worſhip,</hi> becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not foreſee all <hi>Circumſtances</hi> that may make things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>lawful, pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> unlawful. We cannot allow our ſelves the ſame Liberty to practiſe, as our <hi>Phyſician</hi> directs us, for <hi>the Health of our Bodies,</hi> or a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> for the Security of our <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and, as our <hi>Miniſter</hi> directs, <hi>for our Souls,</hi> becauſe we think our <hi>Souls</hi> better than our <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and therefore a Truſt as to them can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo ſafe, but of infinite more Hazard; and beſides, tho' we have not <hi>Avicen,</hi> and <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> to read, and if we had them, we could not underſtand them, and the <hi>Phyſician</hi> preſcribes not <hi>ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem,</hi> but <hi>ad Socratem;</hi> yet we have the Word of God, it is nigh us, in our Eyes and Ears, we can read it, and it preſcribes <hi>ad homines,</hi> the ſame things to all Men, and we are bid to <hi>ſearch it,</hi> and by it to <hi>prove all things,</hi> and then to <hi>hold faſt what is good,</hi> (not in others, but in our own Eyes:) So as, under Correction, the Reaſon is not the ſame for following the Preſcripts of <hi>Divines,</hi> as of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>Lawyers;</hi> yet few Men will follow either of them, if they have any ſtrong Opinion they adviſe them ill, tho' they may, when they have nothing to object to what they preſcribe or adviſe.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Author</hi> is aware, that the <hi>Trumpets alſo may give incertain Sounds, the very Guides and Miniſters of Religion may determine differently:</hi> He directs alſo what to do in this Caſe, <hi>p.</hi> 25, 26.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His firſt Direction is very Reaſonable, <q rend="inline">That thoſe who are able tolerably to judge for themſelves, ſhould not rely upon the Authority of any that do it, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Proſelytes of any, further than they give them good Scripture and Reaſon for it.</q> Let that Soul forfeit the Name of Rational and Religious too, that will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this. This is indeed to make Men <hi>Proſelytes of the Law.</hi> But,</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100797:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. <q rend="inline">For others, he ſaith, (and how to know them he hath not told us,) they had better truſt to, and depend on thoſe Miniſters of known Sufficiency for their Office, who are regularly, and by the Laws of the Land ſet over them, than any other Guides and Teachers that they can chooſe for themſelves. This he ſaith, <hi>To be ſure is the ſafeſt Courſe.</hi>
               </q> But he afterwards tells us, <q rend="inline">He ſpeaks not of ſuch things as concern the Salvation of Men, which are plain and evident to the meaneſt Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, but of Forms and Ceremonies. His Reaſon is, Becauſe, if they chance to miſlead the People, they have ſomething to ſay for themſelves: Their Error is more excuſable and pardonable, as being occaſioned by thoſe to whoſe Judgment, by God's Command, the People owe a great Reſpect and Submiſſion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I know not how we ſhall ever agree here, unleſs in this:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they had better truſt to, and depend upon none at all, but the Judgment of <hi>their own Conſciences,</hi> enlightned firſt, as well as may be, by the Information of thoſe Learned and Holy Men on both ſides, who may in the Point differ one from another, after ſeeking God for his Direction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Truth is, we are for no Truſts, in Matters of <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Duty,</hi> (all which Things we take to be Matters of <hi>Salvation</hi> or <hi>Damnation</hi>) in which Caſe, none ought to truſt any further than they can ſee, tho' they ought to uſe the beſt Means for ſeeing, they can. The taking <hi>Creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> or the Matters of Faith, upon Truſt, is the <hi>Foundation-Error</hi> of <hi>Popery:</hi> He taking <hi>Agenda,</hi> Matters of Practice, wherein the Safety or Eternal Hazard of a Soul is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, is ſomething as bad as <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100797:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. It will puzzle an <hi>Angel</hi> to make us underſtand what <hi>Virtue</hi> or <hi>Ability</hi> there is or can be in a Teacher, whom the Laws of the Land have ſet over us, above what is in one whom God hath ſet over us: There is indeed no Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition betwixt theſe two; God may have ſet one to watch for our Souls, whom the Laws of a Land may authorize to it, but one may by the Laws of a Land be ſet over us, whom God never ſo ſet. He that ſhould ſay, that in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Countries</hi> God hath ſet thoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Confeſſors</hi> over People, whom the Laws of thoſe Countries have ſo ſet, will find it an hard Task to prove what he ſaith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Nor can we underſtand how the <hi>Laws of a Land can ſet Paſtors over Souls:</hi> They can make <hi>Rectors,</hi> and <hi>Parſons,</hi> and <hi>Vicars,</hi> give them <hi>Glebes,</hi> and <hi>Tythes,</hi> and <hi>Houſes;</hi> (but <hi>All Souls are mine,</hi> ſaith God.) We would gladly ſee it proved, that in the Spiritual Concerns of our Souls any can be ſet over us, but thoſe whom God hath ſo ſet, that is, who come to their Places in that <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> which God hath preſcribed. Now that God hath any where directed how <hi>Human Laws</hi> ſhould ſet Paſtors over People, wants better Proof than any we have ſeen: We only reject the Notion till we ſee it prov'd by any Line of Scripture, or any thing which looketh like <hi>Venerable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. We can as little underſtand how any erring, through the Miſtakes of any ſuch Guides, ſhould have this to ſay for themſelves, <hi>Our Error is occaſioned by thoſe, to whoſe Judgments, by thy Command, (O God!) we owed a great Submiſſion?</hi> Where hath God required ſuch a Submiſſion, a Reſpect and Reverence indeed is due; but that a <hi>Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Conſcience</hi> alſo is, we no where find.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our <hi>Author</hi>'s next Direction, is, <hi>throughly to conſider the Nature of Lawful, and how it differeth from what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and what is ſinful.</hi> Who doth not know, that a thing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100797:11"/>
               <hi>lawful is what is neither commanded nor forbidden?</hi> That is, not forbidden, either in the <hi>Letter of Scripture,</hi> or the <hi>true Senſe of it;</hi> either generally, or particularly, or conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially; either in it ſelf conſidered ſeperately from Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or as attended with ſuch or ſuch Circumſtances. <hi>This way of arguing indeed is very plain and convincing;</hi> but if the Meaning be <hi>not forbidden abſtractly,</hi> or in the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Letter of Scripture, it is very <hi>falſe,</hi> and <hi>weak,</hi> and <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author,</hi> p. 28. takes notice of two Miſtakes (as he thinks) upon which Mens Scruples are founded, as to <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That nothing in the Worſhip of God is lawful, but what himſelf hath appointed.</hi> I know none that thinks ſo; there are indeed ſome that think, that <hi>nothing in the Worſhip of God is lawful, which himſelf hath not appointed,</hi> which is idle, and ſuperfluous, and not neceſſary to the Performance of it, upon the Account of <hi>Nature, Conveniency,</hi> or <hi>apparent Decency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither doth any ſay, that thoſe things are unlawful to be uſed in God's Worſhip, which are <hi>neceſſary</hi> upon any of the aforeſaid Accounts, and are but Appendants of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, not entering into the Bowels of it, tho' they have been abuſed in <hi>Idolatrous Worſhip;</hi> for other things, there are many who think them <hi>eo nomine,</hi> unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and may think ſo ſtill, for any thing our Author hath ſaid to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Our Author would have Men to conſider, <hi>That there never was, nor will be, any Conſtitution that will be every way unexceptionable.</hi> If he had ſaid, againſt which none will make Exception, we ſhould have found no Difficulty to have agreed it; but ſurely there may be a Conſtitution that is not <hi>exceptionable:</hi> For if only things confeſſedly <hi>neceſſary be enjoined, and things which may be left at Liberty, be ſo left, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100797:12"/>a little Charity uſed,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Conſtitution</hi> muſt be unexcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Indeed his laſt Direction muſt make an end of all Controverſie of this Nature, if it were practicable, <hi>viz. to throw our Doubts out of our Minds as dangerous Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> This is as if one ſhould adviſe one under a great Fit of the <hi>Stone,</hi> or <hi>Gout, &amp;c.</hi> never to <hi>think of his Pain.</hi> Our Author fancieth rightly, that ſome would be under Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to think, that he hath been perſwading Men to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Orders of the Church, tho' they be not ſatisfied in their Minds concerning them.</hi> He tells us in plain Terms, <hi>He thinks this the beſt Advice can be given ſuch ſcrupulous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> It hath only two Faults, 1. <hi>That it is very hard, if not impoſſible, to be taken.</hi> It is every whit as eaſie to ſhake off a Fit of the Gout or Stone, as to ſhake off a <hi>Doubt;</hi> both may be done in Time, and by the Application of <hi>proper Means:</hi> But I know of none would keep <hi>Doubts,</hi> if they knew how to be rid of them. 2. That it is contrary to the Apoſtle's Opinion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>And he that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is damned, if he eat; becauſe he eateth not of Faith.</hi> The Apoſtle is there plainly ſpeaking of things at that time <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different;</hi> and in all that Chapter he ſaith not a Word of Chriſtians conforming to Practices, <hi>tho' they be not ſatisfied of their Lawfulneſs in their Minds.</hi> Could we but clear our Eyes of <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Paſſion,</hi> (of not immoderate Wrath too againſt our Brethren,) we might ſee better Advice by half given, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not; and let not him that eateth not, judge him that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; for God hath received him:</hi> and, <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Let us not judge therefore one another; but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling-block, or an occaſion to fall, in his brother's way. v.</hi> 14. <hi>To him that eſteemeth any thing to be unclean, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</hi> v. 15. <hi>Deſtroy not him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt died.</hi> If our Author ſhould tell us again, <hi>he takes things as they are,</hi> he doth not <hi>command</hi> theſe things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In caſe they ought not to have been inforced, or at leaſt not at the rate they are, he ought alſo to let them alone as they are.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100797:12"/>Our Saviour reflects on the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Scribes,</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 29. for that <hi>they builded the tombs of the prophets, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the ſepulchres of the righteous;</hi> and yet ſaid, <hi>If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with them in the blood of the prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>He doth not encourage Men to venture blindfold upon Sin.</hi> Is it not Sin then for Men to <hi>eat doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> Is not all Sin that is not of Faith? <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. the Apoſtle there ſaith, <hi>Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind</hi> of the Lawfulneſs of a thing, (for he cannot otherwiſe be interpreted. Our Author tells us, <hi>That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we refuſe to comply with the Orders of a Church</hi> (which poſſibly ought not to have been made, at leaſt we judge ſo) <hi>we ought to be fully perſwaded of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of what is required.</hi> Now is not this to <hi>act Blindfold?</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> indeed was of another Mind, he would have our Eyes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our way; but our <hi>Author</hi> tells us, that if we do not ſee a <hi>plain, deep Pit,</hi> we ought to follow our Mother.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> is aware, <hi>p.</hi> 35. that ſome. would ſay, <hi>This Principle, once imbib'd, will bring in Popery.</hi> All the Anſwer he gives us, is, <hi>That there are many things in Popery mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly evil, and forbidden by the Revealed Will of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then it is granted, that it neceſſarily brings in all that is in <hi>Popery,</hi> that is not <hi>manifeſtly evil;</hi> and that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our <hi>Author</hi>'s Phraſe, <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>we are not fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded is evil.</hi> Welcome then <hi>Oil, Spittle,</hi> and <hi>Cream</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> with an Hundred more ſuch Fopperies: Welcome <hi>Elevations of the Bread,</hi> and the Prieſts many croſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, welcome <hi>Veneration</hi> (tho' not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration) <hi>of Images, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To whom muſt the things be manifeſtly evil? If to <hi>Superiors</hi> only, few things in <hi>Popery</hi> are ſo to their <hi>Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors;</hi> if to <hi>Inferiors,</hi> who ſhall judge whether they be ſo, or no? Shall the Inferior? Then our <hi>Author</hi> hath ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100797:13"/>unleſs to thoſe (which are very few) who think, that in the Worſhip of God, things (confeſſedly indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent) if impoſed, become manifeſtly evil.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author, p.</hi> 35. begins to think of <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19, 23. <hi>To him that eſteemeth any thing unclean, it is unclean;</hi> and, <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>He that doubteth is damned, if he eateth; becauſe he eateth not of faith: whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi> To theſe he anſwers,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>he means by a Scrupulous Conſcience, the Conſcience of a Perſon tolerably perſwaded of the Lawfulneſs of what is to be done; but yet he doth not like it, nor approve of it; he hath ſome little Reaſons and Exceptions againſt it; it is not the beſt and fitteſt, all things conſidered.</hi> He ſhould have done well, firſt to have found out one that owned ſuch a Conſcience, otherwiſe he meaneth none of thoſe he hath all this while been arguing againſt. Surely Men muſt have mighty Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of themſelves, beyond their juſt Stature, that can have ſuch an Opinion as this of all which hath been ſaid in the Caſes in queſtion by Dr. <hi>Ames, Bradſhaw, Calder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Gilleſpy, Cotton,</hi> and an Hundred more. But to what our Author hath here ſaid, I have before ſpake fully.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He anſwers, Secondly, <q rend="inline">That if the Queſtion be about things, wherein we are left wholly to our ſelves, and are at Liberty, having no other weighty Reaſon for the doing of them, then it may be the ſafeſt way to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear all ſuch things as we ſcruple at. But in theſe two Caſes, it is moſt for the Quiet of our Conſciences to act againſt, or, notwithſtanding our Fears and Scruples, when either our Superiors (to whom we owe Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) have interpoſed their Commands, or when by it we prevent ſome great Evil, or Miſchief.</q> Theſe <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors</hi> he makes to be <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100797:13"/>
            <p n="1">1. This now is no more than what indeed Biſhop <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> long ſince ſaid, and we ſhall moſt of us agree with him, and with this Author, in things of meer <hi>Conveniency</hi> and <hi>Expediency,</hi> where we cannot ſin in doing the <hi>one part,</hi> or the other; tho' as to Expediency, <hi>Quicquid non expedit, in quantum non expedit non licet,</hi> is a known Rule amongſt Divines. Things meerly inexpedient, ſo far forth as they are inexpedient, are not lawful, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. But here, how to diſtinguiſh betwixt things of meer <hi>Conveniency</hi> and <hi>Expediency,</hi> we cannot tell, unleſs by Expedient be meant <hi>apparently decent,</hi> whoſe contrary would be <hi>indecent.</hi> If by things expedient be meant <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle doth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. it can by no means be agreed. I think it therefore better expreſſed by <hi>Things in doing or forbearing which we ſhall not ſin againſt God.</hi> In ſuch things, the moſt of us ſhall freely yield what our Author ſaith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if he extends his Notion further than theſe things, we cannot yield what our <hi>Author</hi> ſaith; for then the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s Senſe muſt be, <hi>He that doubteth is damned, if he eateth,</hi> except his <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Superiors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him to eat;</hi> nor will it agree with the next Words, <hi>becauſe he eateth not of faith,</hi> that is, of a full Perſwaſion of the Lawfulneſs of what he doth, unleſs any one will ſay, that is ſufficient to perſwade us fully the thing is <hi>lawful,</hi> if it be commanded by our Superiors, which moſt certainly it is not. This is ſuch an Interpretation of what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, as will ſerve to make all things lawful which the Light of Nature doth not ſhew us an <hi>eternal Turpitude</hi> and <hi>Filthineſs</hi> in. We muſt looſe our Bibles before we can agree this.</p>
            <p>His Second Caſe, wherein he thinks Men may lawfully depart from their <hi>Liberty,</hi> is to <hi>avoid a greater Evil.</hi> This Evil he makes to be <hi>Diviſion from the Church.</hi> Still the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, <hi>Whether Men may depart from their Conſciences
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100797:14"/>for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> Or, Whether Men may do what they verily judge ſinful for them to do, provided it be not againſt the plain Letter of Scripture, but only by them ſo concluded from eaſie Conſequences of Scripture, to keep <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with thoſe that do thoſe things, probably not ſo judging.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> alſo talk'd of, is neither <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Affection,</hi> nor in <hi>Matters Doctrinal,</hi> nor in <hi>Acts of Worſhip,</hi> by God preſcribed, nor in <hi>Modes</hi> or <hi>Circumſtances of Worſhip</hi> ſo preſcribed. The Diſſent is in none of theſe things, but in things (confeſſedly) unneceſſary to be required, as to the End, Conveniency, or apparent Decency of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But in things of <hi>meer Human Appointment,</hi> falling under none of theſe Qualifications, we beg our <hi>Author</hi>'s Pardon for thinking that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in theſe things is not to be preferred before the Satisfaction of our private Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the things are lawful before we do them. I dare aſſure our <hi>Author,</hi> that very many <hi>Diſſenters</hi> will be very well pleaſed with him for propounding to them, <hi>p.</hi> 39. our bleſſed Saviour's Example. His Caſe was this:</p>
            <p>He was born and bred a Member of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, conſtituted by God himſelf, in which Church there were very great Corruptions in the Time when he lived; but the <hi>Law was read,</hi> and the <hi>Paſſover</hi> was adminiſtred in it, which every <hi>Jew,</hi> not being unclean, was bound to eat; the Law was alſo expounded and preached there. He freely reproved, and bare a Teſtimony againſt their <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> and what they had added to the Worſhip of God: He would not religiouſly waſh his Hands before Meat, as our <hi>Author</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>p.</hi> 1, 2. But having a publick Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty himſelf to teach and preach in the <hi>Temple</hi> and in the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> (tho' he had no ſhare in the Revenue of the Prieſts and Levites,) he uſed it, and often heard the Law of his Father opened and read, often reading and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it himſelf; in the mean time he would himſelf have nothing to do with their <hi>Traditions,</hi> (not ſo much as to <hi>waſh his Hands</hi> religiouſly,) but only with his Father's Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100797:14"/>nor did he think himſelf obliged only to preach there, but in many other Places, in <hi>Ships,</hi> upon <hi>Mountains,</hi> in <hi>Private Houſes,</hi> in <hi>Fields,</hi> and that not to Four or Five only, but to Four and Five thouſand. Diſſenters only crave that they may go and do likewiſe: If they may not, this Example is ill produced.</p>
            <p>For the Churches of <hi>Corinth,</hi> &amp;c. they do not think themſelves further bound to follow them than as they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Chriſt, (who did not admit <hi>drunken</hi> Perſons to the Sacrament,) and had our <hi>Author</hi> pleaſed, he could have put a fairer Senſe upon <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> than <hi>drunken;</hi> and ſo our Tranſlators have done, <hi>John</hi> 2.10. where the Tranſlation is, <hi>When men have well drunk,</hi> (yet the ſame Word in the Greek is there uſed,) and that is all meant, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. For as none will ſay that, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.10. it ſignifies <hi>men ſtark drunk;</hi> ſo, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. the Diſorder he reproveth amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> is thus expreſſed, <hi>For in eating, every one taketh before his own Supper, and one is hungry, and another,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hath drunk ſufficiently;</hi> ſo as it ſhould ſeem that they made the Lord's Supper but as a <hi>Banquet;</hi> or <hi>Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cup,</hi> after their own Supper; ſo could not receive it with that <hi>Premeditation,</hi> and <hi>Preparation,</hi> and <hi>Holy Reverence,</hi> which they ought.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> concludes with magnifying of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and perſwading to it, minding us of the high Senſe the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians</hi> and old <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> had of <hi>Diviſion;</hi> and at laſt tells us, <hi>In all that I have now ſaid, I am not conſcious to my ſelf, that I have uſed any Argument but what many of thoſe very Miniſters, who now diſſent from us, did teach and maintain, and print too, againſt the Independants, and other Sectaries that divided from them, when they preached in the Pariſh-Churches. And if this was good Doctrine for thoſe who ſeparated upon the account of Corruptions, for purer Ordinances, in thoſe Days, I ſee not why it is not as good againſt themſelves, when upon the very ſame Pretences, and no other, they divide from us now.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100797:15"/>
            <p>We would willingly know what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> it is they plead for. Is it an Union of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affection?</hi> We profeſs our ſelves ſeperated from no part of Mankind in that Senſe, and more particularly to love our own Nation, all thoſe in it, more eſpecially who are <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and to have a more particular Delight and Complacency in ſuch of them as we ſee live Holy Lives, in a more ſtrict Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to their Rule.</p>
            <p>Is it an Union in <hi>Doctrines?</hi> We have often enough profeſſed our ſelves in Heart to believe all Doctrines of Faith contained in the Holy Scripture, particularly thoſe in the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo far as concerneth Doctrine. In the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Articles, and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Articles, what in this thing can they ask more?</p>
            <p>Is it an Union in the ſame <hi>ſpecifical Acts of Worſhip?</hi> We uſe no other than is and always was uſed in the Church of <hi>England; Prayer, Preaching, Hearing the Word, Baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, Receiving the Lord's Supper,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Is it in the Circumſtances of Worſhip <hi>neceſſary,</hi> as ſome <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> is, ſome <hi>Geſture</hi> and <hi>Habit</hi> is? Was there ever ſuch an Unity, or Uniformity in <hi>England?</hi> Or is there now? Did all People ever meet in the ſame Place, or at the ſame Time, or in the ſame Habits, or uſe the ſame Geſtures? At all times, did not ſome pray ſtanding, ſome kneeling, ſome ſitting? And did they not always as much differ as to their Geſture at the Sacrament? Or <hi>Convenient,</hi> or <hi>obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly decent Circumſtances?</hi> Are then all the Pariſh-Churches equally convenient, or their Pulpits, or Seats, for Preaching or Hearing? Do all Perſons come to Churches in Habits equally decent? Tho', poſſibly, few uſe Habits indecent, which none can charge on us.</p>
            <p>Do not all uſe the ſame Words in Prayer? And do Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts all uſe the ſame, or did they ever uſe the ſame in the Pulpit and the Desk?</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100797:15"/>
            <p>Do we not all meet with them in the ſame Place? Can then all the People in a great Town or City ſo meet? Is the <hi>Diviſion</hi> here then, that we do not agree <hi>Parochial So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties,</hi> to be <hi>particular Churches?</hi> Which amongſt our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Brethren will ſo own them? Surely they reckon the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> the <hi>Particular Church,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> the <hi>Paſtor.</hi> Will not we own <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Government of the Church by them?</hi> We cannot indeed own them by <hi>Divine Right</hi> to have any ſuch Power; but we will own the <hi>King</hi> to be the <hi>Governour of the Church,</hi> under Chriſt, not to make new Laws, but to put his Laws in execution, and to have Power to appoint his <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> under what <hi>Titles</hi> he pleaſeth, (whether <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> or <hi>Biſhops,</hi>) who ſhall have Power (by Virtue of ſuch Commiſſion) to do in the Church what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the King may do; and if theſe <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> be alſo Miniſters of the Goſpel, by Virtue of that Commiſſion from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they ſhall alſo do what any Goſpel-Miniſters may do.</p>
            <p>All the Cry againſt Diſſenters, for <hi>dividing</hi> and rending the Peace of the Church, amounts to this:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they can own no intrinſick Officers in the Church, whom Chriſt hath not appointed in his Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they can own no Laws in Worſhip, but what he hath made by himſelf, or his Commiſſioners the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, till thoſe be proved not to have been ſufficient.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they cannot allow the <hi>Bounds of Pariſhes to be on that account the Bounds of Churches,</hi> nor Inhabitants in them ſufficient to entitle all baptized Perſons to be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church in that Place.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That they cannot agree all Perſons of Sixteen Years of Age, to be fit to receive the Lord's Supper, (a thing never allowed by any Church in the World.) To make the Matter ſhort, <hi>Diſſenters</hi> profeſs themſelves ready to unite with their Brethren in all things relating to Worſhip, for which the leaſt Line of Scripture ſhall be ſhewn, and in other things, if they can be made appear naturally neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the Actions, or <hi>convenient,</hi> or <hi>decent.</hi> We never
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100797:16"/>need fear breaking with them, who will not upon theſe Terms unite with us.</p>
            <p>The Caſe of the Difference betwixt <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Others,</hi> was this: The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were regulating things according to the <hi>Divine Will;</hi> offered their Brethren Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to preach, yea, and in the greateſt Congregations; were ready to hear them in any thing they could object in their Practice, contrary to the Word of God, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any thing; proffeſſed to make nothing their Rule, but the Word of God: They had Reaſon to blame thoſe who on theſe Terms would not unite with them. Are theſe the Terms of Union now offered?</p>
            <p>It may be ſome particular Perſons were too hot at firſt, and ſaid what themſelves afterwards ſaw Cauſe to alter their Minds in, (and that in the Space of two or three Years.) Men, when they are juſt awake, ſee not ſo diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly as they afterwards do. Our firſt Reformers altered many things in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> of which they had a tolerable O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion when they came firſt out of <hi>Popery.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Cranmer</hi> himſelf, and ſome others, thought ſome things at firſt good Doctrine, which themſelves had afterward other Thoughts of, doth it follow it is good Doctrine ſtill? In things of this nature, we are to take our Meaſures from no mutable Men, but from the immutable Rule. <hi>Authority</hi> therefore is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently urged, and is an Argument only <hi>ad excitandum odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> to ſtir up ſome ignorant Peoples Paſſions.</p>
            <p>To let every one ſee the Weakneſs of this Argument, let us turn it into Form.</p>
            <p>Prop. <hi>What was good Doctrine Forty Years ago, in the Mouths of Presbyterians, againſt Independents and Others, is good Doctrine ſtill. But what is in this Sermon about Scrupulous Conſciences, and the Duty of Chriſtians that have them, was good Doctrine Forty Years ſince in the Mouths of the Presbyterians againſt the Independents: Therefore it is good Doctrine ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We deny the <hi>Minor,</hi> or Second <hi>Propoſition,</hi> and ſo take our Leave of the <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſuppoſing it will take <hi>Forty Years</hi> more to make it good.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:100797:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for, and Sold by</hi> Tho. Parkhurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns <hi>in</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>near</hi> Mercers-Chapel.</head>
            <p>EXpoſitory Notes on the Four Evangeliſts; wherein the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Text is at large recited, and the Senſe explained; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Inſtructive Pxample of the Holy Jeſus is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to our Imitation. By <hi>William Burkitt,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divine Comforts Antidoting inward Perplexities of Mind; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Diſcourſe upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> 94. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. By <hi>T. Sharp,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Wilful Impenitency the groſſeſt Self-Murder; in ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Preached at <hi>Rochfort</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> By <hi>William Fenner,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>Plain Method of Catechiſing; ſhewing, That Miniſters, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Maſters, ought to be faithful Teachers of the firſt Principles of the Chriſtian Doctrine. By <hi>T. Doolittle,</hi> M. A. in Compaſſion to the Ignorant.</p>
            <p>The Young Man's Guide in his Way to Heaven; or, Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpiritualized.</p>
            <p>The General Aſſembly; or, the gathering of the Saints toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By <hi>Oliver Heywood,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The Order of the Goſpel profeſſed and practiſed by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>New-England,</hi> in Anſwer to ſeveral Queſtions relating to Church-Diſcipline. By <hi>Increaſe Mather,</hi> Preſident of <hi>Harvard Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge, New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primitia Synagogae;</hi> or, a Sermon Preached at the opening of a New Erected Meeting-houſe in <hi>Ipſwich.</hi> By <hi>John Fairfax,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The Fountain of Life opened and explained; or, a Diſplay of Chriſt, in his Eſſential and Mediatorial Glory; containing Forty Two Sermons on various Texts. By <hi>John Flavel,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Of Thoughtfulneſs for the Morrow, with an Appendix con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the immediate deſire of foreknowing Things to come.</p>
            <p>The Redeemer's Tears wept over loſt Souls, in a Treatiſe on <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. with an Appendix, wherein ſomewhat is occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally
<pb facs="tcp:100797:17"/>Diſcourſed concerning the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and how God is ſaid to will the Salvation of them that periſh.</p>
            <p>A Calm and Sober Enquiry concerning the poſſibility of a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the God-head, in a Letter to a Perſon of Worth; occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by the lately Publiſhed Conſiderations on the Explications of the Doctrine of the Trinity. By Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dr. <hi>South,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> &amp;c. Together with certain Letters (hitherto unpubliſhed) formerly written to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> on the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend concerning a Poſtſcript to the Defence of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Notion of the Trinity in Unity, relating to the Calm Enquiry on the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>A View of that part of the late Conſiderations addreſs'd to <hi>H. H.</hi> about the Trinity, which concerns the Sober Enquiry on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the Soul of Man, wherein the Divine Original, Excellent and Immortal Nature of the Soul, are opened; its Love and Inclination to the Body, with the Neceſſity of its Separation from it, conſidered and improved. The Exiſtence, Operations and States of ſeparated Souls both in Heaven and Hell immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after Death, aſſerted, diſcuſſed, and variouſly applied. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers knotty and difficult Queſtions about departed Souls, both Philoſophical and Theological, ſtated and determined.</p>
            <p>The Method of Grace in bringing home the Eternal Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrived by the Father and accompliſhed by the Son, thro' the Effectual Application of the Spirit unto God's Elect, being the Second Part of Goſpel Redemption.</p>
            <p>The Divine Conduct or Myſtery of Providence, its Being and Efficacy aſſerted and vindicated: All the Methods of Providence in our Courſe of Life open'd, with Directions how to apply and improve them.</p>
            <p>Navigation ſpiritualiz'd, or a new Compaſs for Seamen, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Thirty Two Points of pleaſant Obſervations, profitable Applications, ſerious Reflections, all concluded with ſo many ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Poems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
